Forward reasoning. Okay, so now let's do that proof quickly in Isabelle. So as usual, I started
a special theory file called cases, in the cases demo in this case, and then we want to prove
the following. So we want to prove that X minus Y is smaller than or equal to X. We need to
annotate it with natural numbers, remember, again. And then we can say that the proof goes
by induction on, what did we do in the paper, on the board, so induction and X, that gives
us the base case and the step case. So we prove the base case by using one lemma, using
two lemmas, one that shows that zero minus A equals zero. So let's just see if we have
that lemma. So we have that, zero diff, so we can, so we use that theorem to show that
to say have zero minus Y equals zero. So remember how we did forward reasoning when we didn't
have the, when we didn't have the, when we didn't have any assumptions for the term,
we should say using, and then now you have that goal and that assumption. And you can
always, if you have the goal exactly matching the assumption or that, or, or, or if you have
the assumption more general than the goal in the sense that you can instantiate the
assumption with the goal. So here in this case, we need to instantiate the A with the
Y, which then you can just use the dot is smaller than or equal zero, because we have
a theorem that says anything is smaller than or equal to itself. Let's just find
the theorem name for reflection, that's what it's called. So let's copy it, reflection again
by the dot, then we have the zero is smaller than or equal to zero, then we can say finally
show case and that again, we have the assumption matching the goal. So we can just use the
dot. Okay. Now for the step case, it's a bit more complicated and this is where we need
to do the proof by case splitting. Okay. So if we take the first case, which is, so we
say cases on, what was it, successor of X is greater than or equal to Y. And then it will
do again, it will behave in the same way that we have the induction will suggest to
us proof template. And, but, but in this case, the proof template has two assumptions
instead of having the base case and the step case, where the step case has the induction
hypothesis, as you can see, no, here in this case, we have like case where the, where, where
the case assumption is true. So here you have Y is smaller than or equal to X and here
you have Y is not smaller than or equal to X. So let's start with the first case. So
the first case, the way we proved it was we used successor of a is greater than or equal
to B. So, so we have that we had a lemma that says successor, if the successor of a, yeah,
I think we can generalise that lemma further. So we had the lemma that says we wanted to
say that if the successor, if, if, if the successor of a is more than or equal to B,
then we can have that successor of a minus B to be equal the successor of the whole thing
of a minus B. Yeah, let's see, this is generalizable. Well, okay, so I don't, I don't think we should
prove this theorem now. So the way we do this, we just assume that we have that theorem.
So let's say, let's just call this lemma one and then you have to remove these question
marks and then I will just sort it and then use, yeah, it turns out that, oh, that has to
be greater than. Yeah, it seems like we have a counterexample. So I think we made a mistake
there and that mistake I think is, yeah, that we have the successor there. Like, because
if you have the success, okay, you can see the counterexample. So it says B equals one
and A equals zero. So in this case, you have successor of A, which is one greater than or
equal to B, which is fine. But then you have A minus B, this is zero and successor of
A, sorry, successor of A minus B is zero. And then the successor of A minus B is going
to be one, but the successor of A here is going to be one and one minus one is zero.
So I think we needed a stronger assumption on our lemma and then actually you can find,
automatically find a lemma that has that. So as you can see here in the output panel,
let's go back to the board then and see if the proof will work out given this new
assumption or how can you modify it. So that's how these theorem provers are actually
useful because you can discover mistakes in your reasoning. That's why you use them
to verify systems. So let's see here, where did we make that mistake? This was there.
So here, okay, so if we just remove that successor there from the assumption,
okay, so we have A is equals greater than or equal to B, then this would mean that we need
to actually change our case analysis instead of X, successor of X greater than or equal to Y,
we just change it to X greater than equal to Y and then that was the case here and then
this is there and then this would, so that would go smoothly because you would just still
that assumption, the first case assumption would fit into the assumption of that lemma.
Then you get the conclusion of the lemma that you want and let's see how it will affect the
second case. So here we'll get X is strictly smaller than Y, then in this case we also have
that the successor of X minus Y would be zero. Why is that? Because actually we can modify this
lemma to say if A is more than or equal to B, then A minus B is zero because that also would
hold because if A equals B, then A minus B is zero. So from that, so again, we can use that
to instantiate this assumption and then get that conclusion which would be then, sorry,
which would be, so here we have X is not greater than or equal to Y, so we can from that include
that X is more than Y and from X is smaller than Y, we can conclude that the successor of X is greater
than or equal to Y, just the definition and we will look into that for that lemma in Isabelle.
And then we have here, then the proof can carry on as usual, as we did it originally. So what we need
just is, what we need to modify is just to find the lemma that says if X is smaller than, strictly
smaller than Y, then successor of X is less than or equal to Y and I'll just do that directly in Isabelle.
Okay, so the modified lemma, the correct lemma, actually Isabelle was able to find it,
so it's called SACDIFLE, so this is lemma one. So let's go back to the proof. So instead of saying
successor of X, we just say X is greater than or equal to Y, then let's start with the proof.
So the first case, we had that, we had that the successor of X minus Y equals the successor of X
minus Y with the parentheses on the internal ones and this is pi using that lemma that we just found
there. So that lemma was called, yeah, that's exactly the lemma. But look here, we need to
instantiate that assumption of the lemma and we can see here that assumption with the case
assumption as we did in the board, but the case assumption here is just called true.
So I can, so you can just say, so true, then we have what we want,
then we can, that's the forward reasoning that we're used to or that we did earlier.
And then from that, we have that, we should have that the successor of X minus Y equals
the successor of X minus Y with the parentheses around the whole thing.
And that should hold from, what was it in the proof? In fact, proof from lemma three
and step number one. So what was lemma three? Lemma three was just everything, like anything
is smaller than or equal to itself, less than or equal. So let's just find that lemma that says
it was called order refl, actually, yeah. So we can just copy it from here.
How did you do that? Actually, in there. So we don't have that. So we need to firstly say that
successor of X is smaller than successor of X minus, like successor of X minus Y is more
than or equal to itself using order refl. And then substitute the first step into,
so we call this step one and substitute that step there. So we can say, we can then say
following, how can we do that? So we can just do with the following way. So we can say,
if you remember, I would just call this step number two and then say step number three is that
we have that successor of X minus Y is smaller than or equal to successor of X minus Y like that.
And then I would say using step number one. Okay. So now we have, we have that assumption
and we have that, sorry, using step number two, now we have that assumption and that conclusion.
And we just want to transform that part of the conclusion into this by substitution. So we can,
we can do that by substituting, by doing that substitution there by, by, by applying
step one as a substitution. Then in this case, what do we have here? No, sorry. We need to apply
step one in the other direction, if you remember symmetric. So now we have exactly the conclusion
and the assumption are the same thing. And you can just say a dot, right? So instead of,
so we can say, we can also say here, instead of, if you just want to chain the two tags,
instead of saying have, like instead of, instead of calling this two and then saying have three
from two or have three using two, you can also just say have like this and then say then,
then this is chained and you have that. This is changed, this is exactly like saying using two
earlier. Okay. So now we have done that. And what was the next step in our pen and pen proof?
And then we used another lemma, which was four. And that lemma said that if a is less than or
equal to b, then suck a is less than or equal to suck b. So let's find that theorem and see what
it's called. We don't have it, but I'll just assume we have it. This was called lemma four in
in there. Sorry. So then you can, you can say that,
say also have successor of x, wasn't it? What was the step? So we used lemma four, right?
Using lemma four, but with forward reasoning with induction hypothesis. If you remember,
induction hypothesis is always called suck.ih for natural numbers. And that's the wrong direction.
Because if we do the, yeah, I think that's the wrong direction. We call it both of them are equal,
actually. So we have that. That's the wrong direction. And now we should have the thing
correctly done. Yeah. And finally, you can then say, show pieces. Let's see if they match,
actually. Yeah, they match. So we have done the first case. Now let's look into the second case.
What was it? We needed a lemma that says that if something is not smaller than equal to itself,
to show you something else, wasn't it like that? Then something is not greater or equal than itself.
Then we can, from that, conclude that if a is not greater than equal to b, then we can conclude that,
sorry, if a is not greater than equal to b, then we can conclude that a is strictly smaller
than b. So this is that, not le implies less. So that was the lemma. So then how did the
steps go? So from the case assumption, which is called false in this case, so false is not
y smaller than or equal to x, we should be able to conclude that then have x smaller than y.
Well, using that, so what does this match? Yeah, this would match. So how can we do that? We can just
say, not then have actually, but say using not le of false. Then we have like a forward reasoning
step. And then we say, from that, here we can say that let's just firstly look for the lemma. We
need, the lemma that we need to look for now is lemma that says that if x is smaller than y,
then x is smaller than or equal to y. So let's try and find that. So we have that theorem. And
as you can see, we need to instantiate that assumption for the theorem using forward reasoning
again. So I would just call this 1. And then I would say have suck x more than or equal to y
using suck le forward reasoning 1. And then we have that step. Then from that forward reasoning
step, what was the next thing? We say that suck x minus y equals 0. So let's see, we need a lemma.
If you remember, we had that lemma number 2 on the board that was saying a is smaller than or equal
to b. And that is the lemma that I'm looking for. It makes sense to show it. This one is the lemma
that I'm looking for. So we need a smaller than or equal to b, then a minus b equals 0.
Then let's look for that lemma there. So we say, if a is smaller than or equal to b, then
a minus b equals 0. That is equal to 0. So we can use that to say have suck x minus y equals 0.
How can we do that? We can do it using that lemma and forward reasoning with the previous step.
So we can just say previous step 2. Or we can do it also backward reasoning just to revise that
with you. So you can say apply rule, and then you have that transform the goal from that to that.
And then if we say using 2, then that would satisfy the goal. But I would just keep
using forward reasoning because I think that's what I prefer. Lastly, the second to last step is
step number 4, where we say that 0 is smaller than or equal successor of x. And that is based on lemma
number 6, which was saying that 0 is more than or equal to anything. 0 is smaller than or equal to
anything. So 0le is called. So just copy the name. As you can see, we don't have any assumptions. So
you can just do that. And then the last step, which is step number 5, shows that the successor
of x minus of y is smaller than or equal to x, which is just the goal of our case.
So I'll just say show theses. So here we have x minus y is smaller than or equal to x. So we can
do that by substituting. So we say using 4, if you remember, using 4, and then substituting
the rewrite rule from 3 to transform that part of the goal to a 0. And then we already have that 0
is more than or equal to x in step number 4. So we do that. And what we get, 0 is more than or equal
to x implies 0 is more than or equal to x. And we're done with the proof. So that proof was a bit
longer. But it combines a lot of our techniques. So it combines induction, forward reasoning,
substitution, and case analysis. So I hope that that was understandable. So that's all. Thank you
very much.